[Music]
hi and welcome to this session on what's
new in Excel reports for finance and
sales my name is Brian nilson I'm a
program manager in business Central team
with me I have Kenny yeah my name is
Kenny pontop and I'm also a program
manager in the business Central team and
uh we have a exciting agenda for you
today we've been uh looking forward to
showing you the these new Excel reports
that are coming in the Bas app and we'll
show off uh some of the reports in the
finance area and the sales area then U
we'll also talk about upcoming reports
that are coming in the next waves or
next releases and then no business
Central launch event without co-pilot so
of course we'll demo some Excel co-pilot
on business Central data but let's get
started um first thing about reports is
you need to discover where they are
right so we have at least three ways for
you to do that first of all on the
accountant's um role Center under Excel
report you can find these new they are
marked with preview for now because we
might have some design changes we want
to do but they're fully functional
should be um they would also appear on
because they are on on the the role
Center in the role Explorer or report
Explorer so easiest thing I have is
simply to search for preview um in the
report Explorer and then they pop up
here and then of course you can always
use the tell me search and and they will
also surface here but instead of seeing
how to discover the reports maybe Brian
we should take a look so what's new in
finance what we have here yeah so for
finance we have the trial balance based
reports it's probably the first thing
you want to uh to look at in Excel when
you have a an Erp system um but if you
if we take a look at at my system here
where I have the reports you said the
accountant role center it's actually
also on the uh business manager role
Center and of course you can find them
in in tell me they are placed under
reports for the
business manager role Center we have all
of them all in this release means we
have eight of them the trial balances AG
receivables age payables and the top
list um in the accountant uh role Center
uh we don't have the vendor uh reports
anyway so let's take a a look at at the
reports how they they look in Excel and
for the trial balance based reports
let's just look at the the trial balance
when you select it you get the request
page where you have a few
filters um we Tred to make it as simple
as possible so you won't see that many
filters and parameters because you just
want your data for a report and then you
can refine it in Excel so in this case
we'll just take the first three periods
of data and then we download it and we
can open it from our Explorer and
continue in in Excel so let's look at at
that in Excel you have some sheets in
the Excel workbook the first one is
obviously the trial balance that you
would expect it is laid out as a report
so that you can recognize that this is a
trial balance you got your data that you
uh selected in your request page you
have some slicers for easy filtering if
you want to uh dimensions and account
categories are the ones that we put up
as default you can put up more in some
of the reports in this case it's local
currency additional reporting currency
two different reports they look very
similar except at two different amount
bases there will be Numbers demo data is
a bit sparse but you'll find it here so
you have a report that is laid out as
something you could print so if you
wanted a printed report or present it to
somebody else instead of just a raw data
you have a a template for it you can of
course modify it you have the raw data
and that means you can design your own
reports you can use it to pivot table
you can use it for charting you have the
dimensions if you want to have some
slices that make a lookup something like
that but the
base uh thing with with Excel report is
you get your data but Excel has some
limitations uh Excel cannot handle
millions of rows so for the trial
balance for the trial
balance uh we have decided that the
aggregation level is of course accounts
the periods that you have selected so
you don't have a daily uh
total uh you just have for for the
period but we have broken it down per
Dimension values in this case where we
have also included account categories
there's a further uh breakdown there so
you can have your slices and and do a
bit of slicing and dicing on the data
that you have selected there will be
more reports where you have a a a finer
grain of detail
but you you will then have to limit what
you extract to excel because we have an
upper limit but we found out that when
we're looking at data around at 100,000
rows is what is manageable uh
performance- wise so aggregated data but
it's still a lot more data than you have
in a PDF
report yeah the next set of reports so
um next set is sales because not
everyone is is a lot of Finance like you
do Brian so maybe as a sales manager I
want to contact some customers or maybe
I want to see what they owe us uh with a
accounts can you can we see some of what
that could be used for for the sales
manager yeah so uh where sales and and
finance crosses borders is uh Ace
account receivables uh we also included
just for familiarity the customer top
report and that is the a top list and
because we are in Excel uh you can
select it doesn't have to be top 10 it
can be top 100 or just top
three uh you can do a bit of more
filtering and then download
it the top report will then look like
this it's a very simple report it is it
is a very simple data set we thought
that maybe you just wanted just to have
a list of your your top customers sales
or or balance-wise and we put in a chart
that that's the most simple report you
probably can get in um in business
Central data a accountables is probably
the together with payables the second
most important set of reports you can
have you can have an aging date uh end
of March probably you want to do it by a
due date the usual um period length and
period count will take three periods and
you can skip skip customers with hero
balance you know that from the uh rdlc
report and you can do a bit of filtering
and you can download it again the first
page the first tab in the spreadsheet is
something that looks like um a printable
report you can get you can move the
slices a bit away you can move the the
headers if you want a more condensed
View and or if you have more periods you
can extend it a bit but it's it looks
printable and
presentable we thought by period by
local Curren C by the functional
currency where you get the currency of
the outstanding balance in our demo data
there is only local currency but if
there were more it would be a breakdown
here we can have it due by currencies
it's a different way of of looking at
your data just to show that you now have
data that you can slice and dice and
present in a different way
interactively
again we have aggregated data uh in this
report you don't get all of the detailed
data you do get a detail per per
customer per period uh and again you can
see there's a breakdown in
Dimensions um so if you want the finer
grain of detail you will wait for some
of the coming
releases and I think Brian this also
illustrates that the strength a couple
of strengths for Excel reports like if
you have a a traditional report that
just give you one PDF first of all you
cannot interact so the slicer part you
can't do with PDF and getting the data
set you can't do with PDF all the
self-service for laying out the data you
want is what Excel offers but also these
different worksheets you actually have
one report that covers three reports in
a sense so ability on the same data set
to to offer different views on data is
where Excel really shines yeah yeah but
Brian you also mentioned that we will
have some on some upcoming uh reports so
you mentioned eight is coming here in
version 24 or in the release Wave 1 uh
what else have you up your sleeve here
so uh when we set out to do the Excel
report we had a list of I think it was
35 reports and then when you start
looking at it some other Reports look
similar so you include them in the list
in this release in in in the first wave
uh April wave we have released eight
reports the trial balances and payables
and receivables and the top reports we
want to include uh more Finance reports
the consolidation reports the uh closing
trial balances uh we want to include
more reports for customers and vendors
the balance to dat reports where you
will get the customer and vendor Ledger
entries uh and if you filter so you have
for example last year which hopefully
it's not 100,000 for whatever segment
you're interested in you have your
customer and vendor detail Ledger
entries sorry not the detail Ledger
entries but The Ledger entries where you
can create reports that have a finer
granularity than the aceables and
payables report and then we move on to
uh other areas we focus on sales and
finance and a bit of purchase first and
then we extend to other areas the next
other area is probably going to be fixed
assets um where you have the asset list
and you have depreciations you want to
maybe um combine it what you have in in
purchase and GL uh and then we move on
to some of the other modules the jobs
module manufacturing maybe service maybe
we won't cover all of the reports
because the intent is with Excel you'll
get a a good overview of your business
and then from there on there's probably
better tools and ways to analyze data
but there's a lot more reports coming
for Excel over the coming releases both
in minor releases and of course also in
the next major cool thanks Brian that
looks amazing um also I come from the
platform so actually getting some
reports into the base app is amazing to
see hopefully this will also Inspire
both you as a customer but also Partners
to build your own new Excel reports and
have this new uh new way of interacting
with data in a broader scope all right
co-pilot so
um right now in preview as of April or
March
2024 U there's also new things coming in
Excel and since Excel reports are in
Excel and we also have open in Excel
that gives you data in Excel we thought
wouldn't it be interesting to actually
see what's coming so that once you have
data in Excel you might do your further
data analysis directly there and uh
that's what co-pilot in Excel is all
about first of all go deeper in data
maybe ask questions with co-pilot or get
U understand data better and also
identify insights in data and
specifically for insights the great
thing about machine learning and AI is
that sometimes it's better at looking at
pattern in Greater data sets than we as
people are and and that's actually a
small demo that I think could be
interesting to to have a co-pilot look
at some data sets and identify some some
patterns
all right so Brian you didn't want to
show us the accounts payable report but
this this this report actually had some
funny data to analyze so I picked that
one but I'm not going to use the normal
reports I'll actually just go directly
into the data set and for co-pilots to
have some data to work on it leasts
meets a little bit more than just the
five rows that maybe is is present in
our demo data so what we did was we we
pumped that vendor Hing data up bit so
we now have 100,000 rows of data and
let's see what co-pilot can help us out
so I will just go up here in the ribbon
and activate co-pilot for Excel this is
in preview right now and uh let's see if
we can find some interesting patterns in
our data co-pilot will give us or give
me some choices and I want to analyze
I'll just pick analyze and copilot is
very nice and say is it can analyze data
and it's actually suggesting outlier so
I'll just pick are there any outliers in
my data and let's see what co-pilot come
comes up with understanding your data
great we're almost
there all right so apparently there are
some out outliers in the data set and uh
I would like just to add this to a new
worksheet so I can look more into it and
maybe take this suggested visual that
Excel added for this pivot and see that
apparently there at least four dates in
my data set that look not necessarily
suspicious but these are for this
particular vendor things I might want to
go in and have a second look and that's
also what we always do with co-pilot we
have machine learning on AI to suggest
something for a human being to go and
control so I'm always in the loop I will
go and check these for this vendor these
dates to see if something is odd either
we made a mistake they made a mistake or
maybe it's totally fine transactions
so instead of using the the report and
slice and dice uh yourself to find
something where you have a suspicion
where there's something to look at you
just let co-pilot do that work and you
can spend more time on actually
analyzing data rather than finding data
to analyze so this is just statistics it
might be perfectly fine it might but it
seems that there's some variant that
cannot be explained and that's what
co-pilot in Excel shows
us so to learn more about data analysis
business intelligence reporting
including things in Excel uh go to
aka.ms slbc reporting This is the End
user documentation for this interesting
topic so Brian did we have some Goos for
people to take home yes because there's
a lot of new things to go and do uh
there are new reports um look at them
start analyzing your data uh and maybe
also start using co-pilot to analyze
your data and lastly now that you have a
data set you can go and create your own
report based on these data set and of
course the data sets that come with the
the future reports so start digging into
it so Brian I noticed that you just uh
skipped the report Explorer part which I
think is a shame I know you think it's
like not useful but I actually know that
a lot of users don't know that this
thing exists for discoverability so
maybe next time you go to business
Central go open the report Ro Explorer
and actually see if there are things
there that you never knew existed and go
explore more yeah yeah because it has
all the reports rather than just the
ones that you have in your role Center
or the ones that you know exist it's
it's a nice place to
start finally uh relevant launch
sessions to also watch if you want to
dig more into the editing of layout
maybe for developers is a bit tough but
we do have session for how to do layouts
Excel layouts that are translatable if
you want to do these multilanguage uh
reports so go check that out if you have
a bit of Courage but can I ask do you
need to be a developer you don't
actually need to be a developer to do
excel layouts that's true the only thing
you need a developer for is to to create
the data set that needs to happen in in
a not if not if you're using hopefully
the sooncoming 35 report you can you can
create layouts on top of that right
that's true yeah that's that's one of
the benefits for fixel
yeah as always some general resources
for you uh in business Central so we
have these AKA links we call them aka.
msbc Yammer is where we discuss things
with Partners BC all is for all the like
just like Lord of the Rings this is the
one AKA link to rule them all uh BC
ideas is where you submit ideas for new
features and then on social media X
LinkedIn and so on we are of course
present there so join the conversation
there and finally for office hours both
recordings and live BC office hours is
your friend and with that Brian and I
would like to say thank
you